<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands remembrancers. Or, a word in season to all English men about their elections of the members for the approaching Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E884_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83995)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 133:E884[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands remembrancers. Or, a word in season to all English men about their elections of the members for the approaching Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 1st 1656 scatred about ye streets".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Englands Remembrancers.</hi> OR, A word in ſeaſon to all Engliſh men about their Elections of the members for the approaching Parliament.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Chriſtian friends and Countrey-men</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E have all reaſon to complain, and ſay, this day is a day of trouble, rebuke, and blaſphemy; our country that was great among the nations is now become vile, all her friends have dealt treacherouſly with her, they are become her enemies; how is the profeſſion of holineſſe (by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe amongſt us) blaſted with the names of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, falſeneſſe, ambition and covetouſneſſe? how is the glory and ſtrength of our nation ſpoiled, and the bloud of many thouſands poured forth in waſt like water? how is the treaſure exhauſted, trade and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce deſtroyed? and how are all our rights, liberties and properties inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſubverted by arbitrary powers and force of armes? who can ſay his life or eſtate is ſecured for a moment, if the jealouſie, envy, pride, luſt or covetouſneſſe of ſome in power pleaſe to command it? and how is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction threatned daily by forreign enemies? ſurely the day of the Lord is very great and terrible againſt us, and yet there is mercy with him that he might be feared for in his abundant goodneſſe he ſeems to open a door of hope, and to give us all leave by our Deputies to adviſe the means of our ſafety and peace; and the preſent writts for election of our repreſentatives being the product of divine providence, and we are confident not long ſince, beyond the thoughts of thoſe that ſent them forth, may be juſtly looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the voice of God to you all ſaying; gather the people, call a ſolemn Aſſembly, go and reaſon together, for in the multitude of councell there is ſafety. Dear Chriſtians, it is by the choice of your Deputies only, that the whole body politick of this nation can conſult together for their preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by this means only you may all ſpeak your minds, one to another and every one to the whole nation? it is the naturall way to ſettle your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and provide for your common good, and in your preſent caſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118640:2"/>there is no other way or means conſiſtent with the laws of God, or the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mankind, whereby our breaches can be healed, lawfull powers and authorities created, righteouſneſſe and juſtice exerciſed amongſt us. For which ends we moſt earneſtly beſeech you to be very ſerious and conſiderate in a matter of ſuch high importance, and take heed that you neither miſtake, nor careleſſely ſleight, or neglect your preſent duty, in the choice of your common Aſſembly. Let it not be like a price put into the hands of fools without wiſdome or hearts to uſe it. O that you would all begge of God courage, wiſdome, and faithfulneſſe, impartiality and integrity of heart in this great affaire. Firſt then, miſtake not your preſent duty; think not (as ſome) that your ſtrength in this affair is to ſit ſtill; let not the darkneſſe of unexamined ſcruples prevent your acting in the choice of your repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. It may be ſome of vour tender hearts, being troubled at what hath been done by the Lord Protector (ſo called) are affraid to vote in the choice of your Deputies, leſt you ſhould ſeem to approve his power, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the choice is appointed by his writs: but we pray, examine this better.</p>
            <p>Firſt conſider, that the writs for elections neither did, nor ever could be juſtly conſtrued to give the people any right to chooſe their members of the Parliament; the Almighty God the Creatour, and the fundamentall laws of this nation, gave the people that right by their birth: it was not in the pleaſure of the Kings heretofore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether the people ſhould ever chuſe their Deputies for the common Aſſemblies, though it was left to their diſcretion and prudence what time in the year it was moſt neceſſary to call the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. The Kings were bound by the laws and their oaths to ſend out writs every year to ſummon a Parliament; and the laſt law made about Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ordained the very Conſtables to ſummon the people to the elections, if the Kings and others ſhould neglect their duties to ſummon them; and we hope none of you would have thought that the Conſtables ſummons had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you right to chooſe. The writs are only to call you to exerciſe your own rights, and ſurely you may uſe your own rights whoſoever call you to do it. If a thief ſhould ſtop your way to your own houſe for a time, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſend to you, and bid you go home if you pleaſe; we ſuppoſe none of you would ſcruple to go to your own houſe; why then ſhould you ſcruple (whatſoever you think of the Lord Protector) to uſe your own rights in the expected election, now he permits you to do it, being no way derived or claimed from him? And if it be objected, that the way of elections ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the laws is altered; it is eaſily anſwered, that the diviſions of the numbers of the Electours into ſeverall bodies or meetings, different from thoſe former waies of meeting, change not the rights, and that you uſe your own
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118640:2"/>rights as farre as he will ſuffer you, and it were frowardneſſe to caſt away what you may enjoy, becauſe ye have not all your rights.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome others of you will ſay, that God requires at this time higher waies of advancing Chriſts Kingdome, than by Parliaments, and that God is gone out of the diſpenſation of Parliaments, and therefore you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not look after this to chuſe or to be choſen; but upon due examination this darkneſſe of your minds will vaniſh, and you will find that the Saints pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for Chriſts Kingdome, which God requires, is clothing themſelves with righteouſneſſe. Rev. 19.8. and that no righteous civile powers of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning in this nation can be yet derived from any other fountain then the peoples conſent or choice; and that you cannot be righteous or holy in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up, conſenting, or adhering to any other civile governing powers. 'Tis yet the law given by God, and repeated by Chriſt, that you ſhould do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men, (Saints or not Saints) even as you would that they ſhould do to you. And we do believe that you would not, that any man or men ſhould impoſe laws upon you at pleaſure, and aſſume a power over your lives and eſtates without your conſent; and therefore it cannot be righteouſneſſe in you to do it unto others. Say not therefore that God is gone out of Parliaments, unleſſe you could prove that God hath aboliſhed this old law; or that by ſome other divlne law the power of politick government is now to be der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from other originall then the peoples conſent or choice; and we beſeech you, dear Chriſtians, never fancy that ye are righteous or holie, if the divine laws be not your rule; we can no way ſo highly advance Chriſts Kingdome, as by obeying his laws, and to be found doing them when he comes.</p>
            <p>But ſay ſome others, we dare not have a hand in the choice of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for we doubt they will take away our liberty of conſcience in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God, and we now enjoy it under the Lord Protector, thats worth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all things elſe.</p>
            <p>Dear Chriſtians, we beſeech you trie theſe your fears, whether they be of God; by what you alledge; you ſeem to ſaie, we cannot endeavour to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a righteous government, leſt they oppreſſe our conſciences. Firſt trie whether you can find by ſcripture or reaſon, any other waie (except the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples perſonall agreement) to ſettle a lawfull authoritie in this nation, but by ſome choſen Deputies to repreſent the people, and conſent in their behalfs to ſuch laws as are now neceſſarie for ſafetie, peace, and common right and juſtice a mongſt us; if you can, then there is place for prudence, to adviſe whether your liberties will be ſecure by Parliaments; but if you can find no other juſt means of making our laws, and ſetling a lawfull government, then you muſt either renounce obedience to God, or elſe cheerefullie do your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118640:3"/>dutie, and chuſe your Deputies with wiſdome and integritie, and truſt to the divine providence to bleſſe and protect you and your liberties, whileſt you walk according to his rules, and no queſtion, if there be due addreſſes to God, and dependance upon him (if it be at this time good for his people, and moſt for his honour to preſerve their liberties in his worſhip) he will do it by Parliaments, and will ſmite the hearts of anie that now intend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, as he ſmote the heart of Saul in his journie. Act. 9.4. However you maie more comfortablie depend upon God in purſuing the paths of righteouſneſſe in government, than you can in adhering to anie power aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in unrighteouſneſſe, under good pretences, when the Ark tottered. 2 Sam. 6.6, 7. Vzziah put forth his hand with an intent to ſave the Arke, yet it ceſt him his life, becauſe he took his own way, and not Gods to his good ends. And manie that adhered to Abſolom in his rebellion. 2 Sam. 15, 4. (upon hopes of greater liberty, which he promiſed them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) juſtlie pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with him. God will have juſtice, and mercie, rather than ſacrif ce; and its better to ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, than to enjoy the pleaſures of in for a ſeaſon. yet if your repreſentatives may be duely choſen, and freely conſult without the influence of a Court, or the a we of a mercenarie ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, their own intereſts and concernment bind them, much more than anie Court, ſtanding counſell or arbitrary powers, to provide for liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, they themſelves being ſubject to the laws they make, and being without anie poſſible private intereſt in oporeſſing any mans conſcience, when the others have alwaies an intereſt of their own, croſſe to the peoples, which guides their reſolutions, and may probably lead them to oppreſſe one day the ſame peoples conſcience, that were their ſavourites the daie before.</p>
            <p>But ſome maie yet ſaie, it is to no purpoſe to mind theſe elections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord Protector with his red-Coats will either force them to ſerve his ends, or turn them home again.</p>
            <p>We confeſſe there is much cauſe for theſe fears, yet they are no ground for you to forbear to elect, or to be elected, it cannot be denied that (unleſſe there could be a perſonall agreement of the people) an aſſemblie of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Deputies, is the onlie viſible means to ſettle juſtice, r ght and peace in the nation; and if ſo, then, no fear of the ſucceſſe or of anie danger, can war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the omiſſion or neglect of uſing the laſt or onlie viſible means of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right and ſafetie, when there was no other viſible means left to preſerve her Countrie from ruine, then it was fit for Eſther to attempt that means. Eſther 4.16. (though the Tyrants ſword had decreed it to be death to uſe it) and to crie out if I periſh I periſh: none that love juſtice and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, may omit any one prebable means of their proſperitie and ſafetie.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118640:3"/>
            <p> Secondly, the ſucceſſe of a lawfull means of good ought not to be diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, who knows what Jonathan and his armour-bearer maie do when the ſpirit of God cometh upon them. 1 Sam. 14.6. when Hezekiah had paid Senacharib all his due tribute, and nothing would content him, but that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zokiah and his people muſt be ſlaves, and the people were in great fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his mightie hoſt, what became of his one hundred and eightie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men in a night. 2 Kings 18.14. with 31.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, admit the hopes of good were very ſmall, if the poſſiblt means be not uſed, and juſtice and righteouſneſſe in government be ſubverted, and the name of God thereby blaſphemed and your Countrie ruined, you cannot comfortably ſuffer under it, your conſcience will be galled with remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that you neglected one opportunity that might poſſibly have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented all the miſchief.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if the aſſembly prove fruitleſſe, yet your electing carefully ſuch as you ought may prevent much miſchief; if men of corrupt, rotten princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and of mean baſe ſervile ſpirits ſhould ſtand under the notion of the peoples repreſentatives, by reaſon of honeſt mens negligence about the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; how will the name and glorie of God be eclipſed, that ſhould ſhine forth in laws founded on juſtice and reaſon, and in governours acted by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſanctified principles? how may unrighte ouſneſſe be ſetled by a law; and you and your poſterities ſold for ſlaves, to ſerve like beaſt; the will and luſt of great men; therefore the danger you mention as a diſcouragement in your election, is the greateſt poſſible argument of care and caution in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And if your Deputies ſhould be returned home again, for their fait<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and integrity in their truſt, the ſin be upon their heads that doe r, and the meaſure of their iniquity will be the ſooner full, and fit for divine vengeance. Now as we hope all honeſt men will be ſatisfied, that it is their duties to chooſe their Deputies for the approching Parliament, ſo we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie pray them, not to ſleight their dutie, nor do it negligently. Think not upon this as a ſmall thing, that muſt give place to a bargain, or a daies har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt work, or the ſaving of a load or two of hay or Corn, do not think it of ſuch mean concernment, that it is indifferent with you whether you go to the elections or not, unleſs your friend or your land-lord ſend to you. Let us intreat you to conſider the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of your Dutie and the Importance of it to your ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>You are now to chooſe thoſe that are to judge of all your common grievances and complaints, and to ſtudie and contrive your redreſs, eaſe and happineſs, you are now to chooſe thoſe that are to diſpoſe of and comm<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118640:4"/>your purſes, and to lay what taxes upon you they in their wiſedome ſhall think neceſſary: you are now to chooſe thoſe that are to make warre or peace for you, ſo that the bloud of your ſelves and the whole Countrey, is in effect (under God) bound up in the wiſdome and Integrity of their Reſolutions; they may under God involve you in bloud and Confuſion, or ſettle you in peace and Happineſſe: you are now to chooſe thoſe that are to chooſe for you all the Rules of your civil lives and converſations, they are to judge wherein you ſhall be bound and wherein free. The Rules and Lawes you have already are in their power to alter (ſaving to you your naturall Rights) and what new lawes they judge neceſſary, you are to be bound by them: you are to chooſe thoſe that are to ſuperviſe the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Juſtice amongſt you; ſo that in truth you are now to provide for all righteouſnhſſe amongſt men, wherein the Glory of God, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the profeſſion of Chriſtianity is ſo much concern'd. And in a word, you are now to chooſe thoſe whom you truſt with your perſons, your lives, your eſtates, your wives and children, and your countrey. If you have any value for any of theſe, and love to juſtice, and the Honour of God, and love to your deareſt Countrey, and tenderneſſe to your wives and children, or your own bloud, or any love to your trades, peace and ſafety, you are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to mind this election and to take heed how you chooſe, and whom you chooſe, and to do it conſcionably as in the ſight of God, and not as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſers. Take heed that no vile corrupt motive bias or incline your minds in your Election. Let not any Dependance you have upon any man for perſonall profit and advantage move you, let not friendſhip or relation of any kind whatſoever make you recede from the pure and noble principles of free-born Engliſh men. Let not the greateſt power or pompe of any man make you admire him, or incline your minds to truſt him. Let not hopes of favour or countenance of any man allure you, ſell not your ſelves and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and countrey at ſuch low prices as theſe. Neither let the threats or terrour of any man, nor yet the claſhing of the ſouldiers Armes affright you out of your Impartiall judgements and Integrity in your choice; and we beſeech you lay aſide all perſonall prejudice againſt any ſort of men, and agree together to have nothing in your eyes in your Elections, but the worth and fitneſſe of the perſons for ſo great a truſt as you are to repoſe in them. And enquire after theſe enſuing Qualifications.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they be ſuch men as <hi>Jethro</hi> counſelled <hi>Moſes</hi> to chooſe, men, fearing God, and haring coverouſneſſe, and lovers of righteouſneſſe and truth. <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they be men of judgement and wiſedome, having a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118640:4"/>ſence of, and able to look into the true cauſes of all our Countries miſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es diſtractions and burthens; and by Gods help to contrive the beſt means of our eaſe and ſettlement in freedome and peace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they be men of courage and fortitude, deſpiſing danger and hazard for the common good; ſuch as think not their lives too dear to venture for righteouſneſſe ſake: men of cowardly mean ſpirits will ſell themſelves and you for ſlaves, if any man of power boldly attempt to be a tyrant over you.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that they be men of uprightneſſe and integrity in their lives, ſuch as ſear not good laws but love them; how can evil doers to whom good laws are a terrour be inſtrumentall to make ſuch laws? ſuch as are faith breakers and falſifiers of their truſts, proud and arbitrary, oppreſſours of others, or deſpiſers of the laws; ſuch can never heartily endeavour that juſtice ſhould be done on ſuch offendours, and without that, you can never enjoy freedome or ſafety.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that they be full of mercie, love and goodneſſe to all men, full of the bowells of Chriſt, taking compaſſion of ſuch as are out of the way, not malic ous cruell or blocdy, whoſe hands and hearts are readie to thirſt for the bloud of ſuch as are not of their minds though men more righteous then themſelves.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, that they be men of meek humble and ſober minds, not proud or ambitious, nor paſſionate, ſuch will eaſily degene ate into tyrants, or be readie to ſhare in tyranny.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, That they be men of publick enlarged minds and hearts, who know they are not born for themſelves, but to give glory to God in righteouſneſſe in their generation; ſuch as cannot be ſatisfied unleſſe they be doing good to othe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s; not men of private mean ſpirits who m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd not how the nation fares, if it be well with them; ſuch will be readie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray you to ſave themſelves.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, That they be men equally concerned with you in all they ſhall adviſe about, or enact, whoſe intereſt is bound up in yours, and muſt ſhare equallie in all your common burthens, opp eſſions and loſſes, not ſuch as live upon the publick purſe, or any of their adherents, whoſe gain is your loſſe, and whoſe pomp and greatneſſe muſt be founded in your op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and ruines.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, that they be men of ſound experience in publick affairs and well affected with the worth of our good old cauſe, and well read in the deceipts of this age, and ſuch of whoſe faithfulneſſe you have had ſome try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; ſeek out we ſay, dear Chriſtian friends and Countrey-men, for men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118640:5"/>thus fitted by God for publick truſt, and meet and adviſe together how you may find out men ſo qualified; and then acquaint each other with your knowledge you have of them, and lend ſuch in your ſtead to the Grand Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and then pray for them, and ſtand by them, and take every affront done to them, as done to the whole nation, and to every one of you in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and then without doubt (if God ſhall pleaſe to humble the nation for the ſins which have brought us under all our miſeries) the mighty God will ſo bleſſe all thoſe endeavours that tend to the advancing of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, truth and juſtice, that the voice of Tyranny and Oppreſſion will be no more heard amongſt us; your liberties will be vindicated, your Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and burthens eas'd, the Honour of our Countrey (that now lieth in the duſt among all nations) will be again reſtored; your trades reviv'd, peace and plenty returned, and the Generations yet unborn will have cauſe to bleſſe God for ſuch an Aſſembly: and what ſhall we ſay more to you? dear Chriſtians and Countrymen; Do not the teares of the widow, and the cryes of the fatherleſſe ſpeak? do not your impriſoned friends ſpeak? do not your baniſhed neighbours ſpeak? do not your infringed rights ſpeak? do not your invaded properties ſpeak? do not your gaſping liberties ſpeak? do not your often affronted Repreſentatives, (which have been trod upon with ſcorn) ſpeak?<note place="margin">Witneſſe Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maica.</note> do not your incumbred eſtates ſpeak? do not the bloud of many thouſands ſpeak, ſome ſlain with the ſword, and others killed with hunger? do not the cries of your poor brethren the honeſt Sea men, the wall and bulwark of our Nation againſt forreiners, who have ſo freely venturd their lives upon all juſt accounts and calls, and are now moſt barbarouſly forced from their wives and children to ſerve the ambitious, and fruitleſſe deſignes of one man? do not all your ruines at home and abroad, by land and ſea ſpeak to you? Surely they have loud voices, ſurely they do daily cry in your cares, Help, help, or <hi>England</hi> periſhes.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
